Guide to the Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr. papers, 1960-2011 MS2280.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr. papers
1960-2011
1970-1995
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2280.UA
3 Linear Feet 6 document boxes
Dr. Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr. is a professor of European History at The George Washington University in Washington, D.C. His teaching and publications have focused on the History of France, especially the French Revolution, and European intellectual history. The Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr. papers consist of correspondence dating from 1960 to 2011, with the bulk dating between 1970 and 1995. The correspondence is predominately professional, and includes substantive letters from noted historians, including Jacques Godechot and R. R. Palmer. The correspondence includes letters relating to European history and research projects, academic issues, publishing issues, and personal correspondence with friends and family.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Correspondence, Lecture notes, and Publications, reprints, and interviews.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr., December 30, 2009, (2010.001) and December 6, 2011 (2011.081), March 17, 2012 (2012.034)
Scope and Contents
The Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr. papers consist of approximately 1400 letters, documents, and emails ranging in date from 1960 to 2011, with the bulk dating between 1970 and 1995. The correspondence is predominately professional, and includes substantive letters from noted historians, including but not restricted to, Jacques Godechot, R. R. Palmer, Francois Furet, Albert Soboul, Pierre Chaunu, Dominique Julia, Sergio Moravia, James M. Billington, Rudolph Binion, Crane Brinton, C.G. Gillispie, Lawrence Stone, Alasdair MacIntyre, and Keith M. Baker. The collection contains a substantial portion of correspondence from academics, students, administrators and publishers. The correspondence includes letters relating to European history and research projects, academic issues, publishing issues, and personal correspondence with friends and family. There are also lecture notes and publications and reprints all relating to Dr. Kennedy's scholarly work.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr. was a professor (Emeritus as of 2011) of European History at The George Washington University in Washington, D.C. Dr. Kennedy received his Bachelor of Arts from Johns Hopkins University and his Ph.D. from Brandeis in French history. Before coming to GW in 1973, he taught at Kent State University and at the University of Toulouse in France. His teaching and publications have focused on the History of France, especially the French Revolution, and European intellectual history. He has published five books, among them, "A Philosophe in the Age of Revolution: Destutt de Tracy and the Origins of 'Ideology'" (American Philosophical Society, 1978) and "A Cultural History of the French Revolution" (Yale, 1989), "Secularism and its opponents from Augustine to Solzhenitsyn" (Palgrave MacMillan, 2006) and co-authored "Theatre, Opera and Audiences in Revolutionary Paris" (Greenwood, 1996) and co-edited The Shaping of Modern France: Writings on French History since 1715 Introd. by Crane Brinton (MacMillan, 1969). He is a former fellow of the American Council of Learned Societies and a Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars Fellow in 1983-84. He was nominated for the National Book Award, the Pulitzer Prize, and was listed in the New York Times Book Review's Editors' Choices in July, 1989 for his Cultural History of the French Revolution. He was a nominee for the G.W.Trachtenberg Prize for Teaching in 1997 and served several years as a consultant to the Library of Congress' Kluge Prize Committee. Dr. Kennedy received the 1977-78 ACLS Fellowship and the Earhart Foundation Fellowship, 2007-2008.
Lectures and lecturing; France -- History -- 18th century; French Revolution.; France -- History -- 17th century; Courses and lectures; Lectures; George Washington University. Dept. of History; Godechot, Jacques Leules="aacr" source="naf">Palmer, R. R. (Robert Roswell); Kennedy, Robert Emmet, Dr., Jr.
- Correspondence, 1960-2011; 1970-1995; Series 1; 2 Linear Feet 4 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Documents in this series remain largely in the order in which they were received. Dr. Kennedy bundled his correspondence roughly by topic or correspondent. The processing archivist retained this original order, retaining Dr. Kennedy's folder titles where possible, and arranged the documents chronologically within Dr. Kennedy's groupings. Consequently, researchers will note an overlap in date ranges and subjects between folders.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the correspondence of Dr. Robert Emmet Kennedy, Jr. The series consists of approximately 1400 letters, documents, and emails ranging in date from 1960 to 2011. The correspondence is predominately professional, and includes substantive letters from noted historians, including but not restricted to, Jacques Godechot, R. R. Palmer, Francois Furet, Albert Soboul, Pierre Chaunu, Dominique Julia, James M. Billington, Rudolph Binion, Crane Brinton, C.G. Gillispie, Lawrence Stone, Alasdair MacIntyre, and Keith M. Baker. The series contains a substantial portion of correspondence from academics, students, administrators and publishers. The correspondence includes letters relating to European history and research projects, academic issues, publishing issues, and personal correspondence with friends and family.
  - Correspondence, 12 May 1975 - 18 May 1998 and undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Cultural History, Readers' List, 10 December 1986 - 27 July 1990 and undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Destutt de Tracy" publication correspondence, Cambridge Uniersity Press, Yale, etc. and Book proposals/abstracts, 31 July 1973 - 6 April 1993 and undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Famous European and American Academics [1/2], 07 March, 1969- 25 May, 2007; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Famous European and American Academics [2/2], 07 February,1970 - 09 December, 1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence, including GW 1970s, 01 May, 1975- 29 June, 1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence-Jacques Godechot, 13 November 1967- 12 April, 2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kluge Prize and Historical Society, 1998-2008 and undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous 1990s Foundational Documents, 12 May 1997; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Professional Correspondence, 20 December, 1969- 20 September, 1978; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Professional correspondence- Brandeis, Toulouse, George Washington University, 10 March, 1969- 16 June, 2000 & Undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-professional, Routine [1/2], 21 March, 1970- 15 October, 1991; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-professional, Routine [2/2], 31 March, 1993- 19 July, 1995 and Undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence- R.R. Palmer, 04 April, 1974- 02 August, 2002 and Undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence- Publishers, 27 July, 1977- 11 September, 1995 and Undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence- Peter Hill, Chairs of History Dept., 23 August, 1977- 09 June, 1973; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Editor of American Philosophical society, Philadelphia, on publication of "A Philosophe in the Age of Revolution: Destutt de Tracy and The Origins of Ideology", 23 October, 1975- 22 June, 1978 and Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Professional correspondence with Cambridge University Press & other presses regarding Dissertation on Destutt de Tracy, 01 February, 1973- 07 July, 1974 and Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Professional correspondence- historians, funding, publishers, Europe, 17 March, 1976- 10 July, 1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Professional correspondence (incl. French) with historians, conferences, GWU matters, [1/2], 21 December, 1978- 10 December, 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Professional correspondence (Incl. French) with historians, conferences, GWU matters, Reviews, applications, readers' reports [2/2], 08 January, 1982- 16 February, 1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Professional correspondence, 01 July, 1980- 17 December, 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Professional correspondence, 05 January, 1982- 12 July, 1990; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 30 January, 1985- 29 November, 1992; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Professional correspondence (mostly passive), cultural history and female revolution [1/2], 21 January, 1989- 07 August, 1990; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Professional correspondence (mostly passive), cultural history and female revolution [2/2], 15 August, 1980-14 December, 1988; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Professional correspondence, 09 April, 1996- 11 October, 2007; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Professional correspondence, Routine and Domestic, 28 February, 1993- 27 September, 2009; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Professional), 1995-1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Research proposals, Undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yale University Press correspondence, Undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes and clippings, 1973-1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Speaking engagements, clubs, and organizations, 1991-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Dispute over editing of a book review, 1982; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Lecture notes, 2010-2011, undated; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  Arranged in no particular order.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of R. Emmet Kennedy Jr., December 6, 2011 (2011.081)
  This series contains lecture notes and notes on readings used in lectures.
  - Eighteenth Cent. Enlightenment Fr Rev, undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hist. 40 Twentieth Century, undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Russian Revolution, undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 17th c. Intell - Decartes, Louce, Newton, Pascal, undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hist 39 Rennaissance and Reformation, undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hist 39 Antiquity, undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Pre-socratics and Plato undergraduate notes, 1960; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - GW Syllabi, 2010-2011; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Publications, reprints and interviews, 1969-1997; Series 3; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  This series contains reprints and publications.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Braudel, 1976; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    General
    Braudel is a 1976 interview not a publication.
  - Culture revolution papers [1/2], 1969-1990; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Culture revolution papers [2/2], 1969-1990; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Decrets d'Urgence, undated; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    "Decrets 'urgence are notes for a yet to be published article.
  - Pre 1996 theater publications and papers, 1979-1996; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Reader's reports on Cultural History, 1982; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Reprints, 1989,1997; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 9)